Finding Aid for Beth Bashert Papers, 1988-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Beth Bashert Papers 1988-2010
Bashert, Beth.
7.62 MB online
1.4 linear feet
04105 Aa 2
Beth Bashert is a local activist, identified with gay-lesbian issues in Ypsilanti, Michigan. She is an outspoken advocate for civil rights and as a campaign organizer, she has impacted local elections in Ypsilanti and other Michigan cities. The collection consists of organizational materials and topical files pertaining to her political and advocacy activities in Ypsilanti and at the state level.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 9511 ) was first received from Beth Bashert in 2004.
The collection is open to research.
Throughout her life, Beth Bashert has been involved in various local civil rights and political causes. In 1988, she participated in a rape awareness project, designed to highlight the incidence of rape in Ann Arbor. A group of women, who called themselves Survivors of Sexual Assault, painted "A Woman was raped here" on or nearby 300 sites in Ann Arbor. Other causes would follow. In 1996, she participated in the planning for a recreational center for the gay, lesbian, bi-sexual, transgender (GLBT) community to be called the Jane Addams Memorial Center. Although the Center never materialized, primarily for financial reasons, Bashert continued to fight for causes for importance to the GLBT community.
Bashert devoted much energy to Citizens for Community, a group which she co-chaired with Paul Heaton and which was initially organized in April 1997 to urge passage of an anti-discrimination ordinance in Ypsilanti. With essentially the same membership, a second organization - Campaign for Equality - began mobilizing support within the community for the proposed ordinance. Bashert co-chaired the CFE effort along with Lisa Zuber. CFE helped to identify and organize local support, raised the necessary funds, and engaged the support of other organizations. The Ypsilanti City Council passed the ordinance on December 16, 1997, but the issue did not rest there as the opposition sought to overturn the ordinance through a ballot referendum. On the ballot in both 1998 and 2001, Bashert and others successfully organized the campaign to defeat the proposals viewed by many as anti-gay initiatives.
Bashert had become an experienced campaigner, able to enlist stronger, statewide and nationwide support because of her work beginning in 1999 as founding president of Michigan Equality. Michigan Equality (ME) was, according to its mission statement, a statewide, political advocacy non-profit corporation dedicated to "building a broad base of support to end discrimination based on sexual orientation, gender identity or non conformance to gender stereotypes." In 2001, Bashert served as ME board president. Here, she was instrumental in successfully organizing citizens in Michigan cities, particularly in Kalamazoo, Traverse City, and Huntington Woods, to pass city ordinances to include protection from discrimination based upon sexual orientation.
There were other issues of concern to Bashert. In 1998, she used her organizational skills with the Save Our Land, Save Our Future (SOLSOF) campaign that successfully mobilized voters in Washtenaw County for a yes vote on the Farm/Open Space Referendum. In Washtenaw County, Proposition 1, the Comprehensive Land Preservation Strategy, provided a funding mechanism for the purchase of development rights (PDF) from local farmers wanting to protect their farmland from development. Bashert served as campaign coordinator of this effort co-chaired by Keith Molin and Lana Pollack. From 1999 to 2001 Bashert was the regional organizer for the National Abortion and Reproductive rights Action League (NARAL), implementing its Choice for America project to identify pro-choice voters in Michigan.
Beth Bashert lives in Ypsilanti with her long-term partner, Lisa Bashert.
The papers of Beth Bashert document her career as a community activist from 1988 to 2003, with digital material dated. The collection is divided in two series reflecting the arena of activity: Ypsilanti Area Activities and Michigan Statewide Activities.
Subjects:
Bashert, Beth.; Gays--Michigan.; Campaign for Equality (Organization); Lesbians--Michigan.; Michigan Equality (Organization); National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)--Politics and government.
- Ypsilanti Area Activities
  The Ypsilanti Area Activities series documents a variety of activities beginning with her work with the rape awareness project in 1988. A significant set of files relate to the Jane Addams Memorial Center. Included are papers demonstrating Bashert's support for GLBT community needs: child care, counseling, and other services. The next portion of the files - Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality - contains papers from the two campaigns seeking reversal of Ypsilanti's anti-discrimination ordinance. Copies of the official filings with the State of Michigan on fund raising efforts for the 1998 and the 2001 campaigns are included, as well as minutes, correspondence, clippings, and collected information about those individuals (Reggie White, Adele King, Tom Monaghan, and Reverend Levon R. Yuile), who opposed the ordinance.
  - Rape Project 1988, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 1)
  - Washtenaw Rainbow Action Project 1996 (Box 1)
  - Jane Addams Memorial Center 1995-1996
    - Business Plan (Box 1)
    - Floor Plan (Box 1)
    - Legal
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Flying Pig Productions, Inc. 1996
        - Legal papers (Box 1)
        - Product (Box 1)
      - Real Estate Purchase (Box 1)
      - When Pigs Fly DBA 1995 (Box 1)
    - Programming (Box 1)
  - Campaign for Equality 1997-2001
    - Citizens for Community 1997 (Box 1)
    - Ypsilanti Campaign for Equality 1997-1998
      - Campaign Strategy 1998, 2001 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Financial Report (Box 1)
      - Fund Raising State Filing 1998, 2001, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Minutes (Box 1)
      - Press Releases/Media List (Box 1)
      - Publicity/Clippings (Box 1)
  - Save Our Land, Save Our Future 1998
    - Clippings (Box 1)
    - Organizational (Box 1)
  - Shelter Association of Washtenaw County 2002-2003 (Box 1)
- Michigan Statewide Activities
  Michigan Statewide Activities series contains papers relating to Bashert's activities for the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League and Michigan Equality from 1999 to 2002. The Michigan Equality files include board documentation, some meeting agenda, and budget information, strategic plans, and correspondence from 2000 to 2002. The Michigan Equality Board Note Books volume contains by-laws, meeting agenda and minutes, and treasurer reports for the Michigan Equality Group, Michigan Equality Education Fund, and Michigan Equality Political Action Committee. Also found in the volume are Michigan Equality "General" 2002 annual report, outline of the board member responsibilities, grant summaries, and other administrative information. Election Campaigns files include documentation and clippings about activities employed to mount successful election mobilizations in support of local anti-discrimination ordinances. Funding support from the Human Rights Foundation and Pride PAC enabled Bashert to lead an aggressive effort to provide campaign training, voter identification programs, professional and volunteer personnel, and financial consulting to local groups in Michigan cities, notably Traverse City, Kalamazoo, and Huntington Woods. Also included in this series is a monograph Gay Rights at the Ballot Box by Amy L. Stone (University of Minnesota Press, 2012). Digital "Bashert files" contain press releases, spreadsheets, fundraising letters, public relations forms, etc.
  - National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League
    - Choice for America, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Crisis Pregnancy Centers, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan Equality (Box 2)
    - Administrative 2000-2002
      - Board (Box 2)
      - Board Note Books, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - Budget (Box 2)
      - Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Minutes (Box 2)
    - Election Campaigns 2001-2002
      - Strategy
        - Human Rights Campaign (Box 2)
        - Voter Identification (Box 2)
      - Target Cities
        - Grand Ledge (Box 2)
        - Huntington Woods (Box 2)
        - Kalamazoo (Box 2)
        - Royal Oak (Box 2)
        - Traverse City (Box 2)
      - Year in Review 2001 (Box 2)
      - Gay Rights at the Ballot Box by Amy L. Stone (Box 2)
    - Topical Files
      - American Family Association (Box 2)
      - Charter Amendment for Public Transit 2010 (Box 2)
      - Pride PAC (Box 2)
      - "Bashert Files", .ZIP file